<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Open Source Virtual Machine projects</title>
    <author email="joewhaley@users.sourceforge.net">John Whaley</author> 
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Open Source Virtual Machine projects">
<table border="1" width="100%">
  <tr>

    <td>Project Name</td>
    <td>Author</td>
    <td>License</td>
    <td>JDK Version</td>
    <td>Platforms</td>
    <td>Language</td>

    <td>Threads</td>
    <td>GC</td>
    <td>JIT</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://www.kaffe.org/"><b>Kaffe</b></a></td>
    <td>Tim Wilkinson, et al.</td>

    <td>GPL</td>
    <td>1.2 (partly)</td>
    <td>x86, sparc, m68k, arm, mips, alpha, ppc, parisc<br/>
      Windows,<br/>
      Unix variants, DOS</td>
    <td>C</td>

    <td>OS Threads</td>
    <td>Conservative Mark/Sweep</td>
    <td>Slow as hell</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="9"><p>Kaffe is a cleanroom, open source implementation of a Java
      virtual machine and class libraries.</p>
      <p>This is the oldest and by far the most complete clean room open source
      Java virtual machine implementation.  However, the <a href="http://www.shudo.net/jit/perf/index.html">performance
      leaves a lot to be desired</a>.</p></td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://latte.snu.ac.kr/"><b>LaTTe</b></a></td>
    <td>MASS Lab, Seoul National University</td>
    <td>BSD-like</td>
    <td>1.1 (No AWT)</td>
    <td>Sparc</td>

    <td>C</td>
    <td>OS Threads</td>
    <td>Fast incremental</td>
    <td>Adaptive</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="9"><p><em>LaTTe</em> is a virtual machine which is able to execute
      Java bytecode. It includes a novel JIT compiler targeted to RISC machines
      (specifically the UltraSPARC). The JIT compiler generates RISC code of
      good quality through a clever mapping of Java stack operands to registers
      with a negligible overhead. Additionally, the runtime components of LaTTe,
      including thread synchronization, exception handling, and garbage
      collection, have been optimized. As a result, the performance of LaTTe is
      competitive with that of <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jdk/1.2/">Sun's
      JDK 1.2 production release</a> and <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.3/">JDK
      1.3 release candidate client/server VMs (HotSpot)</a>.</p>
      <p>Originally based on <a href="http://www.kaffe.org/"><b>Kaffe</b></a>,
      this has come a long way.</p></td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><b><a href="http://intel.com/research/mrl/orp/">Open Runtime Platform</a></b></td>
    <td>Intel Research</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>x86 on Linux, Windows</td>

    <td>C</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>Multiple</td>
    <td>Multilevel</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="9"><p>ORP, Open Runtime Platform, implements advanced JIT and GC
      interfaces. These interfaces allow the JIT, GC and remaining runtime
      system to be developed in complete isolation and at independent rates. A
      major benefit is that JIT and GC researchers are relieved of the
      intractable task of developing a full system before they can innovate in
      their area of expertise.</p>
      <p>The basic system incorporates a fast code generating JIT as well as an
      optimizing JIT. It also includes several GC algorithms, ranging from a
      simple mark-sweep algorithm to an advanced train algorithm.</p></td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><b><a href="http://www.blackdown.org/java-linux.html">Blackdown JDK for
      Linux</a></b></td>
    <td>Blackdown development team</td>
    <td>Sun CSL</td>
    <td>1.3</td>
    <td>ppc, x86, s390, sparc, arm</td>

    <td>C</td>
    <td>Green / Native</td>
    <td>Conservative Mark/Sweep</td>
    <td>None</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="9"><p>Blackdown was the first group to port Java 1.0, 1.1, and
      then 1.2 to Linux.</p>
      <p>Basically an uninspiring reference implementation, but the only one for
      Linux until fairly recently.</p></td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://kissme.sourceforge.net/"><b>kissme</b></a></td>
    <td>John Leuner, et al.</td>
    <td>GPL</td>
    <td>1.2 (Classpath, No AWT)</td>
    <td>x86, Linux</td>

    <td>C, JIT is in Java</td>
    <td>OS Threads</td>
    <td>Conservative Mark/Sweep</td>
    <td>None yet, plan to write in Java</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="9"><p><b>kissme</b> started its life as a Honours project by
      Stephen Tjasink while he was studying at the University of Cape Town.
      Initially the JVM was developed for a set-top box that came with a TV
      Satellite Decoder. To fulfill this goal the JVM was designed to run on a
      slow processor and with limited memory. One of unconventional aspects of
      the project was the need to store class files in ROM. The JVM was modified
      to be able to store the runtime class information on the ROM and then load
      it again when booting.</p>
      <p>When Stephen did his Masters degree the next year, he decided to extend
      the VM to support <b>orthogonal persistence</b>. Persistent programming
      languages allow the programmer to indicate which objects in memory should
      be saved on secondary storage. The runtime (or a compiled in library) will
      ensure that the data is saved automatically and transparently on disk.
      When the program restarts it can retrieve this information transparently.</p>

      <p>It uses Classpath libraries.  JIT work started in February 2000,
      still not completed.</p></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://sablevm.org/"><b>SableVM</b></a></td>
    <td>Sable group at McGill</td>
    <td>GPL</td>

    <td>1.2 (Classpath)</td>
    <td>x86, Linux</td>
    <td>C</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>Precise copying collector</td>
    <td>None</td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="9"><p>SableVM is an open-source virtual machine for Java, intended
      as a research framework for efficient execution of Java bytecode. The
      framework is essentially composed of an extensible bytecode interpreter
      using state-of-the-art and innovative techniques.</p>
      <p>Interpreter-only, just barely runs &quot;Hello, world!&quot;. However,
      they have some interesting techniques for run time services (thin locks,
      etc.)</p></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://www.japhar.org/"><b>Japhar</b></a></td>

    <td>Petter, et al.</td>
    <td>LGPL</td>
    <td>1.2 (Classpath)</td>
    <td>x86, sparc, arm<br/>
      Unix variants,<br/>
      Win32, BeOS</td>

    <td>C</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>? (None?)</td>
    <td>None</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="9"><p>Japhar is the <a href="http://www.hungry.com">Hungry
      Programmers'</a> Java VM. It has been built from the ground up without
      consulting Sun's sources.</p>
      <p>Development seems to be slow.  Moving from version 0.08 to 0.09
      took 18 months (?).</p></td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://www.complang.tuwien.ac.at/java/cacao/"><b>CACAO</b></a></td>
    <td>Andreas Krall</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>1.0.2</td>
    <td>Alpha</td>

    <td>C</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>Simple</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="9"><p>CACAO is 64 bit just-in-time (JIT) compiler for Java. It
      translates Java byte code on demand into native code for the ALPHA
      processor.</p>
      <p>This doesn't seem to be in development anymore.</p></td>

  </tr>
</table>
</section>
<section name="Open Source JIT compiler projects">
<table border="1" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td>Project Name</td>
    <td>Author</td>
    <td>License</td>

    <td>VM</td>
    <td>Platforms</td>
    <td>Language</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://www.openjit.org/"><b>OpenJIT</b></a></td>
    <td>Tokyo Institute of Technology</td>

    <td>BSD-like</td>
    <td>Any</td>
    <td>Sparc</td>
    <td>Java</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="6">The OpenJIT project is an ongoing Java (the programming
      language) JIT compiler project as a collaborative effort between Tokyo
      Institute of Technology and Fujitsu Laboratory, partly sponsored by the
      Information Promotion Agency of Japan. OpenJIT is a &quot;reflective&quot;

      JIT compiler in that not only it is almost entirely written in Java, but
      also that it bootstraps and compiles itself during execution of the user
      program, and compiler components coexist as first-class objects in user
      heap space. Thus, users can tailor and customize the compilation of
      classes at runtime for variety of purposes such as application-specific
      optimization and partial evaluation, dynamic, compiler-assisted
      environment adaptation of programs, debugging, language extension and
      experimentation, and other types of advanced compiler-based research and
      applications. OpenJIT even allows full dynamic update of itself by loading
      the compiler classes on the fly from the network.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://sax.sax.de/~adlibit/"><b>TYA</b></a></td>
    <td>Albrecht Kleine</td>
    <td>GPL</td>
    <td>Blackdown, BSD</td>

    <td>x86</td>
    <td>C</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="6"><p>TYA is a JIT-compiler designed as an add-on to the Blackdown
      and BSD ports of JDK 1.1 and JDK 1.2 for x86-Linux and FreeBSD. TYA is
      ``100% unofficial'', in no way related to Sun.</p>
      <p>Really, really slow JIT.</p></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>

    <td><a href="http://www.shudo.net/jit/"><b>shuJIT</b></a></td>
    <td>Kazuyuki Shudo</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>Linux, BSD</td>
    <td>x86</td>
    <td>C</td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="6"><p>ShuJIT is a Just In Time compiler (JIT) for Sun
      Microsystems' Java Virtual Machine (JVM) (i.e. JDK, JRE) and Intel IA-32
      (x86) processors. It works on Linux and FreeBSD.</p>
      <p>Performance is <a href="http://www.shudo.net/jit/perf/index.html">average</a>. 
      He has <a href="http://www.shudo.net/photo/0006-JavaGF/000605/index.html">my
      photo</a> on his page, from Java Grande 2000.</p></td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/ef/"><b>ElectricalFire</b></a></td>
    <td>Mozilla.org</td>
    <td>Netscape PL</td>
    <td>Mozilla</td>
    <td>x86</td>

    <td>C</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="6"><p>ElectricalFire is a Java Virtual Machine that uses JIT (Just
      In Time) compilation techniques to accelerate Java code execution. 
      ElectricalFire was designed from the start to generate high-performance
      machine code and to be portable to many different processor architectures.</p>
      <p>It hasn't been updated in over a year.  This project is dead.</p>
      <p>A team of programmers two months to get Sieve to compile correctly...</p></td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://citeseer.ist.psu.edu/cierniak96briki.html"><b>Briki</b></a></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td>Kaffe</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="6">Briki is a now defunct research project to implement an
      optimizing JIT, which was based on Kaffe.</td>
  </tr>
</table>
</section>
<section name="Open Source VM extension projects">
<table border="1" width="100%">
  <tr>
    <td></td>

    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td colspan="9"></td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://www.cs.utah.edu/projects/flux/java/alta/index.html"><b>Alta</b></a></td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>GPL</td>

    <td>?</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>?</td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="9">The Alta Virtual Machine is a Java-compatible Virtual
      Machine designed to provide <a href="http://www.cs.utah.edu/projects/flux/fluke/html/">nested
      process services</a> to Java applications. Alta is based on <a href="http://www.kaffe.org">Kaffe</a>.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://www.dcc.unicamp.br/~oliva/guarana/"><b>Guaraná</b></a></td>

    <td></td>
    <td>GPL</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="9">Guaraná is a reflective architecture that aims at
      simplicity, flexibility, security and reuse of meta-level code. It uses <a href="http://www.kaffe.org/">Kaffe</a>
      as its base.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://kiev.forestro.com/"><b>Kiev</b></a></td>

    <td></td>
    <td>GPL</td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>
    <td></td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="9">Kiev is a compiler which extends and unite Java and Prolog.
      A version of <a href="http://www.kaffe.org">Kaffe</a> is used as a virtual
      machine to provide support for extended bytecode.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/~susan/"><b>PJama</b></a></td>

    <td>University of Glasgow and SunLabs</td>
    <td>?</td>
    <td>1.1.7</td>
    <td>N/A</td>
    <td>N/A</td>
    <td>N/A</td>

    <td>N/A</td>
    <td>N/a</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="9"><p>The PJama started in September 1995 with funding from <a href="http://www.sun.com/">Sun
      Microsystems</a> for an investigation into the feasability of support for
      orthogonal persistence in the programming language <a href="http://java.sun.com/">Java</a>.
      A subsequent <a href="http://www.dcs.glasgow.ac.uk/pjava/pix5-fun.jpg">PJava
      project</a> proposal for &quot;PJava: High Performance Orthogonally
      Persistent Java Servers&quot;, highly-rated by the <a href="http://www.epsrc.ac.uk/default.htm">EPSRC
      (Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council)</a>, provides further
      funding.</p>
      <p>Based on the standard JDK 1.1.7 source code.</p>

      <p>The project ended in September 2000.</p></td>
  </tr>
</table>
</section>
<section name="Other Related Open Source projects">
<table border="1">
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://gcc.gnu.org/java/"><b>gcj</b></a></td>
    <td>RedHat</td>

    <td>GPL</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="3">GCJ is a portable, optimizing, ahead-of-time compiler for
      the Java Programming Language. It can compile...
      <ul>
        <li>Java source code to native machine code,</li>
        <li>Java source code to Java bytecode (class files),</li>
        <li>and Java bytecode to native machine code.</li>
      </ul>

    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://oss.software.ibm.com/developerworks/opensource/jikes/project/"><b>Jikes</b></a></td>
    <td>Dave Shields and Phillipe Charles</td>
    <td>BSD-like</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td colspan="3">Jikes is a compiler that translates Java source files as
      defined in <a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/jls">The Java
      Language Specification</a> into the bytecoded instruction set and binary
      format defined in <a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/vmspec">The
      Java Virtual Machine Specification</a>. Features include:
      <ul>
        <li>strict adherence to the language specification,</li>
        <li>extremely fast compile speed,</li>
        <li>built-in dependence analysis, allowing incremental compilation and
          automatic makefile generation.</li>
      </ul>

    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/classpath/classpath.html"><b>GNU Classpath</b></a></td>
    <td>???</td>
    <td>GPL</td>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <td colspan="3">GNU Classpath is a set of essential libraries for supporting
      the Java language. The goal is to provide a free replacement for Sun's
      proprietary class libraries so that the GNU system can run programs
      written in the Java language.</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td><a href="http://sources.redhat.com/mauve/"><b>Mauve</b></a></td>
    <td>???</td>
    <td>GPL</td>

  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td colspan="3">The Mauve Project is a collaborative effort to write a free
      test suite for the Java class libraries.</td>
  </tr>
</table>
<h4></h4>
<h4>Non-open source stuff</h4>
<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.borland.com/jbuilder/">Borland JBuilder JIT
    compiler for Linux</a></li>

  <li><a href="http://naturalbridge.com/">BulletTrain</a>
    static compiler by NaturalBridge</li>
  <li>IBM JDK</li>
  <li>Official port for the <a href="http://www.freebsd.org/java/">Java for
    FreeBSD</a></li>
</ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
