<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>What's new for joeq</title>
    <author email="joewhaley@users.sourceforge.net">John Whaley</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="News and Status">
      <h3>January 24, 2005</h3>
      <ul>
        <li>Updated web site to be autogenerated nightly using Maven.</li>
      </ul>
      <h3>June 12, 2003</h3>
      <ul>
        <li>I'm going to make a new release in a couple days for all the IVME people. Stay tuned!</li>
      </ul>
      <h3>March 15, 2003</h3>
      <ul>
        <li>I've written an overview of the joeq system. Highly recommended to anyone interested in joeq.</li>
        <li>I'm getting ready for another binary release on SourceForge. Stay tuned.</li>
        <li>I'll update the web pages soon, I promise ;-).</li>
      </ul>
      <h3>October 10, 2002</h3>
      <ul>
        <li>The transition to symbolic 'Address' types has been complete. The bootstrapper has also been greatly improved.</li>
      </ul>
      <h3>August 1, 2002</h3>
      <ul>
        <li>So many things have changed! The big news today is our Linux release. Check it out on SourceForge downloads page! I will be gradually updating the web pages to match the current state of the project.</li>
      </ul>
      <h3>April 16, 2001</h3>
      <ul>
        <li>joeq successfully runs all of the SpecJVM benchmark suite in command-line mode.</li>
      </ul>
      <h3>April 9, 2001</h3>
      <ul>
        <li>M:N threading support has been implemented and is working correctly! The scheduler supports fully preemptive multitasking. Along with this, we have implemented a fast thin locking mechanism with lock expansion upon contention.</li>
      </ul>
      <h3>March 11, 2001</h3>
      <ul>
        <li>Native zip/jar file support has been added, even when bootstrapping. (I have extended the reflection mechanism to support execution of code to recreate state.) Thus, there is no more need to extract classes from zip/jar archives before using joeq.</li>
      </ul>
      <h3>February 26, 2001</h3>
      <ul>
        <li>joeq now outputs object files in standard COFF format. Thus, you no longer need to use a special loader -- you can now use a standard linker.</li>
      </ul>
      <h3>February 5, 2001</h3>
      <ul>
        <li>SourceForge has enabled my account, so I put up the code and web pages.</li>
      </ul>
      <h3>February 2, 2001</h3>
      <ul>
        <li>I've put up a design document.</li>
      </ul>
      <h3>February 1, 2001</h3>
      <ul>
        <li>Project registered with SourceForge.</li>
        <li>Initial alpha release.</li>
      </ul>
      <hr noshade="" size="1"/>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
